David Stick Papers PC.5001
State Archives of North Carolina
David Stick Papers
circa 1750-2009 and undated
PC.5001
5000.6.806
155.500 122.130 1.000
David Stick was an author, historian, researcher, realtor, real estate speculator, philanthropist, and public figure active on the Outer Banks of North Carolina from the 1930s to the late 2000s. He spent his life accumulating a massive library of monographs, serials, maps, and manuscript materials which became the founding collection of the Outer Banks History Center in 1986. Stick, along with his father, Frank Stick, are were influential figures in Outer Banks history, and they were involved with numerous major developments in the area, such as the creation and preservation of the Cape Hatteras National Seashore, the development of the town of Southern Shores, the passage of the Coastal Area Management Act, and the erection of milepost markers along NC Highway 12 in Dare County. Stick was heavily involved in dozens of organizations and agencies based on the Outer Banks, including the Dare County Tourist Bureau, Outer Banks Community Foundation, and Coastal Resources Commission. The David Stick Papers, circa 1750-2009 and undated, contains materials related to the organizations and agencies with which Stick was affiliated, drafts and publication information related to his various writing projects, personal and family papers, business records, research files, and photographs.
Stick, David, 1919-2009
Outer Banks History Center
Box Box 1
Box Box 2
Box Box 100
Box Box 101
Box Box 102
Box Box 103
Box Box 104
Box Box 105
Box Box 106
Box Box 107
Box Box 108
Box Box 109
Box Box 10
Box Box 110
Box Box 111
Box Box 112
Box Box 113
Box Box 114
Box Box 115
Box Box 116
Box Box 117
Box Box 118
Box Box 119
Box Box 11
Box Box 120
Box Box 121
Box Box 122
Box Box 123
Box Box 124
Box Box 125
Box Box 126
Box Box 127
Box Box 128
Box Box 129
Box Box 12
Box Box 130
Box Box 131
Box Box 132
Box Box 133
Box Box 134
Box Box 135
Box Box 136
Box Box 137
Box Box 138
Box Box 139
Box Box 13
Box Box 140
Box Box 141
Box Box 142
Box Box 143
Box Box 144
Box Box 145
Box Box 146
Box Box 147
Box Box 148
Box Box 149
Box Box 14
Box Box 150
Box Box 151
Box Box 152
Box Box 153
Box Box 154
Box Box 155
Box Box 156
Box Box 157
Box Box 158
Box Box 159
Box Box 15
Box Box 160
Box Box 161
Box Box 162
Box Box 164
Box Box 165
Box Box 166
Box Box 167
Box Box 168
Box Box 169
Box Box 16
Box Box 170
Box Box 171
Box Box 172
Box Box 173
Box Box 174
Box Box 175
Box Box 176
Box Box 177
Box Box 178
Box Box 179
Box Box 17
Box Box 180
Box Box 181
Box Box 182
Box Box 183
Box Box 184
Box Box 185
Box Box 186
Box Box 187
Box Box 188
Box Box 18
Box Box 191
Box Box 192
Box Box 193
Box Box 194
Box Box 195
Box Box 196
Box Box 197
Box Box 198
Box Box 199
Box Box 19
Box Box 200
Box Box 201
Box Box 202
Box Box 203
Box Box 204
Box Box 205
Box Box 206
Box Box 207
Box Box 208
Box Box 209
Box Box 20
Box Box 210
Box Box 211
Box Box 212
Box Box 213
Box Box 214
Box Box 215
Box Box 216
Box Box 217
Box Box 218
Box Box 219
Box Box 21
Box Box 220
Box Box 221
Box Box 222
Box Box 223
Box Box 224
Box Box 225
Box Box 226
Box Box 227
Box Box 228
Box Box 229
Box Box 22
Box Box 230
Box Box 231
Box Box 232
Box Box 233
Box Box 234
Box Box 235
Box Box 236
Box Box 237
Box Box 238
Box Box 239
Box Box 23
Box Box 240
Box Box 241
Box Box 242
Box Box 243
Box Box 244
Box Box 245
Box Box 246
Box Box 247
Box Box 248
Box Box 249
Box Box 24
Box Box 250
Box Box 251
Box Box 252
Box Box 253
Box Box 254
Box Box 255
Box Box 256
Box Box 257
Box Box 258
Box Box 259
Box Box 25
Box Box 260
Box Box 261
Box Box 262
Box Box 263
Box Box 264
Box Box 265
Box Box 266
Box Box 267
Box Box 268
Box Box 269
Box Box 26
Box Box 270
Box Box 271
Box Box 272
Box Box 273
Box Box 274
Box Box 275
Box Image Box 1
Box Image Box 2
Box Image Box 3
Box Image Box 4
Box Box 27
Box Image Box 5
Box Image Box 6
Box Image Box 7
Box Image Box 8
Box Image Box 9
Box Image Box 10
Box Image Box 11
Box Image Box 12
Box Image Box 13
Box Image Box 14
Box Box 28
Box Image Box 15
Box Image Box 16
Box AV Box 1
Box AV Box 2
Box AV Box 3
Box AV Box 4
Box AV Box 5
Box Oversize Box 1
Box Oversize Box 2
Box Oversize Box 3
Box Box 29
Box Oversize Box 4
Box Box 30
Box Box 31
Box Box 32
Box Box 33
Box Box 34
Box Box 35
Box Box 36
Box Box 37
Box Box 38
Box Box 39
Box Box 3
Box Box 40
Box Box 41
Box Box 42
Box Box 43
Box Box 44
Box Box 45
Box Box 46
Box Box 47
Box Box 48
Box Box 49
Box Box 4
Box Box 50
Box Box 51
Box Box 52
Box Box 53
Box Box 54
Box Box 55
Box Box 56
Box Box 57
Box Box 58
Box Box 59
Box Box 5
Box Box 60
Box Box 61
Box Box 62
Box Box 63
Box Box 64
Box Box 65
Box Box 66
Box Box 67
Box Box 68
Box Box 69
Box Box 6
Box Box 70
Box Box 71
Box Box 72
Box Box 73
Box Box 74
Box Box 75
Box Box 76
Box Box 77
Box Box 78
Box Box 79
Box Box 7
Box Box 80
Box Box 81
Box Box 82
Box Box 83
Box Box 84
Box Box 85
Box Box 86
Box Box 87
Box Box 88
Box Box 89
Box Box 8
Box Box 90
Box Box 91
Box Box 92
Box Box 93
Box Box 94
Box Box 95
Box Box 96
Box Box 97
Box Box 98
Box Box 99
Box Box 9
Box AV Box 6
Box AV Box 7
Box AV Box 8
Box David Stick Papers
Item 2019 Addition Maps
Box Box 276
Arrangement
Original order and original folder titles have been retained when possible. Stick's original folder numbers have not been retained. Arrangement differs by series and subseries but is usually alphabetical or chronological.
Access Restrictions
Available for research. Audiovisual materials may be inaccessible pending reformatting. Contact the Outer Banks History Center for more information.
Separated Material
Monographs, serials, and most maps have been separated and cataloged individually as the David Stick Library. Clippings received prior to 2012 are filed in the Outer Banks History Center vertical files.
Biographical/Historical
David Stick was born 21 December 1919 in Interlaken, New Jersey, to Frank Leonard Stick (1884-1966) and Ada Maud Hayes Stick (1889-1972). He had one older sister, Charlotte Stick McMullan (1909-1969). He was educated in the public school system of Asbury Park, New Jersey, before moving to Skyco on Roanoke Island, North Carolina, with his family in 1929. He finished his primary education at Manteo Public Schools and attended Elizabeth City High School, graduating in 1936. While at Elizabeth City High School he edited the student newspaper, The Loudspeaker. He wrote his first column for the Elizabeth City Independent at age 15 and served as the Dare County Bureau Manager for the Daily Advance in his late teens. After graduation, Stick attended Vermont Academy in Saxtons River, Vermont, for one year before returning to North Carolina to attend the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. He quit college in 1938 and never obtained a degree.
Stick's early career was spent as a freelance writer, contributing articles to newspapers such as The Coastland Times and The Seashore News. He served as a combat correspondent for the United States Marine Corps from 1942 to 1945. From 1945 to 1947, he served as associate editor for American Legion Magazine. In 1948, he focused his writing efforts on books, publishing his first book, Fabulous Dare, in 1949. A full list of both published and unpublished books written by Stick can be found in a separate note in this finding aid.
Stick engaged in a variety of professional projects over the course of his life. He became the first licensed realtor on the Outer Banks in 1947 and remained active in the real estate field for the duration of his career. He served in founding and/or leadership roles in Kitty Hawk Enterprises, St. John Land Company (based in the U.S. Virgin Islands), Southern Shores Realty Company, Kitty Hawk Land Company, Outer Banks Contractors Inc., and Southern Shores Motor Lodge Inc. Stick was influential in developing the town of Southern Shores, which began as a planned community. He would eventually serve as the town's first mayor. From 1949 to 1953 he operated a craft shop, Kitty Hawk Craft Shop, with his wife. Stick was also active as a book dealer, operating North Carolina Books from 1962 to 1972. He used the proceeds from his book business to fund acquisitions for his research library. In 1976, he sold all his remaining business interests and retired.
Stick was also involved in numerous organizations, associations, and civic groups on the Outer Banks. He was involved with many groups from the time of their founding, including the Dare County Tourist Bureau, Outer Banks Recreation Association, Dare Beaches Chamber of Commerce, Outer Banks Chamber of Commerce, and Dare County Erosion Control Board. He was a co-founder and president of the Outer Banks Community Foundation, and his personal library and papers formed the basis of the collections of the Outer Banks History Center in 1987. Stick also served on a number of commissions and committees at the state level, including the Carolina Charter Tercentenary Commission, Carolina Charter Corporation, Governor's Commission on Library Resources, North Carolinians for Better Libraries, North Carolina Marine Science Council, Americas 400th Anniversary Committee, North Carolina Coastal Resources Commission, and Historical Society of North Carolina. In addition to serving as mayor of Southern Shores, he was also elected to the Dare County Board of Commissioners and chaired the board from 1958 to 1962. He received numerous awards and recognitions, including the University of North Carolina's Distinguished Alumni Award (1982), North Caroliniana Society Award (1987), and the Order of the Longleaf Pine (1996).
Stick married Phyllis Stapells in 1948, whom he eventually divorced. The couple had three children: Michael Alan (born 2 June 1954), Gregory (born 23 October 1955), and Timothy Bryan (born 26 May 1958). Stick died in 2009 at the age of 89.
David Stick Bibliography
Fabulous Dare, Dare Press, 1948.
Graveyard of the Atlantic, UNC Press, 1952.
The Outer Banks of North Carolina, UNC Press, 1958.
The Cape Hatteras Seashore (with Bruce Roberts), Heritage, 1964.
Dare County: A History, NC Division of Archives and History, 1970.
Aycock Brown's Outer Banks, Donning, 1976.
North Carolina Lighthouses, NC Division of Archives and History, 1980.
An Artist's Catch: Watercolors by Frank Stick, UNC Press, 1981.
Roanoke Island: The Beginnings of English America, UNC Press, 1983.
Bald Head: A History of Smith Island & Cape Fear, Broadfoot, 1985.
The Ash Wednesday Storm, Gresham, 1987.
An Outer Banks Reader, UNC Press, 1998.
Unpublished Writings by David Stick:
The Currituck Doctor
Mann's Harbor
Musings of a Maverick
David Stick Narratives
Outer Bankers to be Remembered
Custodial History
Some portions of this collection were originally separated into discrete collections and given their own collection numbers. When the David Stick Papers was fully processed in 2018-2019, these materials were reintegrated. A list of these materials, including their defunct collection numbers, titles, and where they can now be found in this collection, follows.
33GRF-4 Interviews of Dr. Charles Wright by David Stick: See boxes 130-132, AV boxes 2, 3, and 6.
33GRF-26 Ash Wednesday Storm Photographs. See image box 3.
33GRF-28 David Stick Photographs: See image boxes 1-15.
33GRF-33 The Cape Hatteras Seashore, Photographs used in the book by David Stick and Bruce Roberts: See image box 16.
33GRF-58 Ash Wednesday Storm Photographs: See image box 3.
5AUD-15 Interviews Conducted by David Stick: See AV boxes 1-2.
33MSS-7 David Stick Hurricane Research Materials: See boxes 257 and 258.
33MSS-20 Dare Beaches Water and Sewer Authority and Dare Beaches Water Study Group Documents: See box 113.
33MSS-35 David Stick Narratives: See boxes 147 and 148.
33MSS-38 Collection of Dredge and Fill Requests Near Whalebone Junction: See box 258.
33MSS-42 Statistics of Paupers, Dare County: See oversize box 1.
33MSS-51 Photostats of Wright Papers Quoted in "The Outer Banks of North Carolina": See oversize box 2.
33MSS-78 An Outer Banks Reader Research Materials: See boxes 164-167.
33MSS-100 The Outer Bankers To Be Remembered by David Stick Manuscript Collection: See box 151.
33MSS-0-80 Original Report of William Tatham on the Survey of the Coast of North Carolina from Cape Fear to Cape Hatteras, 1806: See box 265.
33MSS-0-85 Various papers on shellfish landings, finfish landings, crabmeat pickings and shrimp landings: See box 265.
33MSS-0-94 From David Stick to Mr. James M. Stewart: Requesting Copies of Several Different Water Resources Research Institute Reports: See box 185.
33MSS-0-95 From Mr. James Stewart to David Stick: Cover Letter Upon Sending of Several Reports to Mr. Stick: See box 185.
33MSS-0-191 [Transcript of Interview with David Stick]: See box 206.
Provenance
Donated by David Stick in various accessions, 1986-2012. 2 boxes containing clippings and Musings of a Maverick materials donated by Brewster Brown, who purchased them at an auction, December 2017. "A Place Called Jockey's Ridge" manuscript with Stick's comments donated by Jockey's Ridge State Park, June 2019
Frank Stick Papers and Artwork from Stick, Frank,(collection 194)
Maud Hayes Stick Papers from Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972,(collection 1013)
Dare Coast Pirates Jamboree Collection from the Outer Banks History Center,(collection 5305)
Scope and Content
The David Stick Papers, circa 1750-2009 and undated, contains correspondence, meeting minutes, ephemera, personal papers, financial records, audiovisual materials, photographs, and maps created or collected by Stick over the course of his life. Materials are arranged into six series: Organizations and Agencies, 1930-2009 and undated; Writings, 1813-2009 and undated; Personal Papers, 1907-2009 and undated; Business Papers, 1910-1997 and undated; Research Files, circa 1750-2007 and undated; and Photographs, 1909-2008 and undated.
In some cases, materials related to a particular subject or entity appear in multiple series, and descriptive notes have been added to indicate this. Generally, researchers should review the entire finding aid when attempting to locate relevant material on any one topic.
Bridgers, Henry C., Jr. (Henry Clark), 1913-1981; Stick Family; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972; Stick, Frank; Stick, David, 1919-2009
Dare County Tourist Bureau (Dare County, N.C.); North Carolina. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee; North Carolina Coastal Resources Commission; Outer Banks Community Foundation; Outer Banks History Center
Dare Coast Pirates Jamboree
Ash Wednesday Storm, 1962; Coastal Zone Management--North Carolina; Beach Erosion--North Carolina; Hurricanes--North Carolina; Lighthouses--North Carolina; Postal Service--North Carolina--Dare County; Real estate development--North Carolina--Dare County
Cape Hatteras National Seashore (N.C.)--History; Dare County (N.C.)--Board of Commissioners; Dare County (N.C.)--History; Dare County (N.C.)--Maps; Kill Devil Hills (N.C.)--History; Kitty Hawk (N.C.)--History; Manteo (N.C.)--History; Nags Head (N.C.)--History; Ocracoke (N.C.)--History; Outer Banks (N.C.)--Biography; Outer Banks (N.C.)--History; Outer Banks (N.C.)--Environmental conditions; Outer Banks (N.C.)--Maps; Outer Banks (N.C.)--Social conditions; Outer Banks (N.C.)--Social life and customs; Southern Shores (N.C.)--History; Virginia Dare Shores (N.C.); Wright Brothers National Memorial (N.C.)
- Organizations and Agencies, 1930-2009 and undated; 45072; Stick, David, 1919-2009
  Scope and Content
  The Organizations and Agencies series, 1930-2009 and undated, contains records collected by David Stick related to various organizations, committees, and agencies with which he was affiliated or in which he had a specific interest. Many of the organizations in this series were founded or co-founded by Stick, and he operated in an advisory or ex-officio role in many others. In most cases, the material in this series dates from Stick's direct involvement with the organization in question; records created by an active organization after his departure are generally scant or nonexistent. Specific content varies by subseries, but documents in this series largely comprise meeting minutes and agendas; correspondence between Stick and other members of the organization, as well as third party contacts; programs, flyers, and other ephemera created for events organized by the group; foundational and administrative records, such as bylaws, articles of incorporation, and tax documents; financial records such as budgets and treasurer's reports; copies of bills and other legislative documents created by the North Carolina General Assembly or United States Congress affecting the organization; and reports and publications. Please see subseries-level descriptive notes for more information on each organization and the materials related to it. For additional material (clippings) on many of the organizations in this series, see the Clippings subseries of the Research Files series. For copies of speeches and related material associated with speaking events at which Stick appeared on behalf of some organizations in this series, see the Speeches and Speaking Engagements subseries of the Writings series.
  - America's 400th Anniversary Committee (AFHAC), 1955-1989 and undated (bulk 1978-1987); 1978-1987; 6674; Stick, David, 1919-2009
    America's 400 anniversary was observed in North Carolina from 1984 to 1987, commemorating the quadricentennial of the attempts by Sir Walter Raleigh to colonize what are now the Outer Banks of North Carolina. A statewide committee was appointed to plan and oversee the anniversary events, and David Stick served on the committee. This subseries contains Stick's personal copies of the committee's records, including letters and memoranda between committee members and various related organizations and individuals; information regarding publications and creative works written for the event; records of archeological explorations conducted under the auspices of the anniversary; event programs, brochures, pamphlets, invitations, and other ephemera related to the celebrations; and reports, financial documents, budgets, membership rosters, and other records created by the committee.
    - Bed and Breakfast Bill, 1983; 26158; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Bed and Breakfast Bill)
    - Budgets, 1979-1983; 26159; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Budgets)
    - British-American Festival, 1978-1984; 26160; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder British-American Festival)
    - Commemorative Events - Miscellaneous, 1980-1984; 26161; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Commemorative Events - Miscellaneous)
    - Commemorative Events - Dare County, 1980-1986; 26162; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Commemorative Events - Dare County)
    - Commemorative Products, 1980-1984; 26163; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Commemorative Products)
    - County Committees - Dare County, 1980-1985; 26164; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder County Committees - Dare County)
    - County Committees - Miscellaneous, 1981-1986; 26165; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder County Committees - Miscellaneous)
    - Educational Programs, 1982-1985; 26166; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Educational Programs)
    - Endorsed and Sanctioned Activities, 1980-1984; 26167; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Endorsed and Sanctioned Activities)
    - England, Activities In, 1981-1987; 26168; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder England, Activities In)
    - Executive Committee, 1982; 26169; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Executive Committee)
    - Executive Director's Reports, 1984-1985; 26170; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Executive Director's Reports)
    - Exhibitions: Raleigh and Roanoke, 1980-1985; 26171; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Exhibitions: Raleigh and Roanoke)
    - Exhibitions: This Sceptered Isle, 1986; 26172; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Exhibitions: This Sceptered Isle)
    - Finances, 1981-1984; 26173; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Finances)
    - Fort Raleigh National Historic Site, 1974-1979; 26174; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Fort Raleigh National Historic Site)
    - From Devon to Dare - Album, 1983; 26175; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder From Devon to Dare - Album)
    - Governor's Business Council, 1978-1980; 26176; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Governor's Business Council)
    - Governor's Conference on Travel and Tourism, 1984; 26177; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Governor's Conference on Travel and Tourism)
    - Green, Paul, 1978-1981; 26178; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Green, Paul)
      Includes two original letters of thanks addressed to David Stick from Paul Green, as well as a note of sympathy from the committee sent to Green's wife on the occasion of his death in 1982.
    - Indian Activities and Issues, 1981-1986; 26179; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Indian Activities and Issues)
      Contains extensive documentation surrounding the committee's decisions regarding the portrayal of Indigenous peoples during the anniversary celebrations. Members of the North Carolina Bureau of Indigenous Affairs, as well as individuals across the state, expressed concern to the committee that Indigenous North Carolinians have a role in the 400th anniversary celebrations and that historical Indigenous populations be honored during the observance. The committee responded by appointing an Advisory Committee on Native American Participation as well as and proclaiming 1986 the Year of the Native American. Included in this folder are letters from David Stick responding to expressions of concern about Indigenous representation in the celebrations, and letters from A. Bruce Jones, executive director of the North Carolina Commission on Indian Affairs, regarding efforts to involve his constituents.
    - Jones, H.G., 1979-1980; 26180; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Jones, H.G.)
    - Logo & Seal, 1980; 26181; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Logo & Seal)
    - Lost Roanoke Colony Script, 1979; 26182; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Lost Roanoke Colony Script)
    - Manteo Committee, 1980; 26183; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Manteo Committee)
    - Manteo, Town of, 1980-1981; 26184; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Manteo, Town of)
    - Members, 1978-1984; 26185; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Members)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980-1984; 26186; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Miscellaneous)
    - Neville, John, 1980-1987; 26187; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Neville, John)
    - Operation Raleigh, 1984-1985; 26188; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Operation Raleigh)
    - Organizational and Background Material, 1978-1980 and undated; 26189; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Organizational and Background Material)
    - Priority Poll of Members, 1980; 26190; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Priority Poll of Members)
    - Public Relations, 1982-1986; 26191; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Public Relations)
    - Quadricentennial News, 1981-1987; 26192; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Quadricentennial News)
    - Roanoke Island Historical Association, 1982-1987; 26193; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Roanoke Island Historical Association)
    - Scope of Activities, 1979; 26194; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Scope of Activities)
    - Sir Walter Raleigh Conference, 1982-1987; 26195; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Sir Walter Raleigh Conference)
    - Southern Historical Association (1983 meeting), 26196; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Southern Historical Association (1983 meeting))
    - Status Reports, 1982; 26197; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Status Reports)
    - Status Reports, 1983; 26198; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Status Reports)
    - Status Reports, 1984; 26199; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Status Reports)
    - Status Reports, 1985; 26200; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Status Reports)
    - Status Reports, 1986; 26201; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Status Reports)
    - Status Reports, 1987; 26202; Stick, David, 1919-2009 (Folder Status Reports)